<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://jameslieu.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://jameslieu.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-08-21T15:58:11+01:00</updated><id>http://jameslieu.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">James Lieu</title><subtitle>Software Developer</subtitle><author><name>James Lieu</name></author><entry><title type="html">Introduction To Cucumber</title><link href="http://jameslieu.github.io/introduction-to-cucumber/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduction To Cucumber" /><published>2020-08-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-08-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://jameslieu.github.io/introduction-to-cucumber</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://jameslieu.github.io/introduction-to-cucumber/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/cucumber-tests-1.png&quot; style=&quot;height: 50px; margin:0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-cucumber-&quot;&gt;What is Cucumber? 🥒&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cucumber.io/&quot;&gt;Cucumber&lt;/a&gt; is an open source tool for running automated tests written in plain language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because they’re written in plain language, they can be read by anyone involved with the product development. And it can be used to help improve communication, collaboration and trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/cucumber-tests-2.png&quot; style=&quot;height: 200px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cucumber reads executable specifications written in plain text, it validates the software’s behaviour based on those specifications and they consist of multiple scenarios and each scenario has a list of steps for Cucumber to work through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It verifies that the software conforms with the specification and generates a report, indicating success or failure for each scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order for Cucumber to understand the scenarios, they must follow some basic syntax rules, called Gherkin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gherkin-syntax-&quot;&gt;Gherkin Syntax 💬&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Gherkin is the language Cucumber uses to define test cases. It’s a set of grammar rules that makes plain text structured enough for Cucumber to understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/cucumber-tests-6.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Example of Gherkin Syntax&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s designed to be non-technical, human readable, and collectively describes use-cases relating to a software system and seeks to enforce firm, unambiguous requirements. As well as document how the system behaves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/cucumber-tests-5.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Gherkin also supports over 70 languages, this is written in Portuguese&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;keywords-&quot;&gt;Keywords 🔍&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gherkin uses a set of special keywords to give structure and meaning to executable specifications. Most lines in a Gherkin document start with one of those keywords.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;-feature&quot;&gt;⛲ Feature&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the Feature keyword is to provide a high-level description of a software feature, and to group related scenarios. The first primary keyword in a Gherkin document must always be Feature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;-scenario-or-example&quot;&gt;❎ Scenario or Example.&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a concrete example that illustrates a business rule which consists of a list of steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can have as many steps as you like, but it’s recommended not to have too many. Having too many steps in an scenario, will cause it to lose it’s expressive power as specification and documentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;steps-&quot;&gt;Steps 👣&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Given&lt;/strong&gt; steps are used to describe the initial context of the system. It’s typically something that’s happened in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Cucumber executes a &lt;strong&gt;Given&lt;/strong&gt; step, it will configure the system to be in a well-defined state, such as creating and configuring objects or adding data to a test database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;When&lt;/strong&gt; steps are used to describe an event, or an action. This can be a person interacting with the system, or it can be an event triggered by another system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Then&lt;/strong&gt; steps are used to describe an expected outcome, or result. It should use an assertion to compare what the system actually does, to, what the “Step” says the system is supposed to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/cucumber-tests-3.png&quot; style=&quot;height:320px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Example “Steps” of an API call to search for a contact&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have successive &lt;strong&gt;Given’s&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;When’s&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;Then’s&lt;/strong&gt;, you can use &lt;strong&gt;And&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;But&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-definitions-&quot;&gt;Step Definitions 💭&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cucumber tests are divided into individual Features. These Features are subdivided into Scenarios, which are sequences of Steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steps can be considered a method invocation. Before Cucumber can execute one, it must be told how that step should be performed via a Step Definition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Step definitions are the glue between, features written in Gherkin, and the actual test’s implementation.
They connect Steps to programming code and carries out the action that should be performed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/cucumber-tests-4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Step Definitions for the above “Steps” example&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are methods with an expression, that links it to one or more Steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when Cucumber executes a Step in a scenario, it will look for a matching Step Definition to execute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-points-&quot;&gt;Key Points 🔑&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So just to run through some of the key points&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cucumber is an Open source tool for test automation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It reads executable specifications written in plain text.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The test-cases are written in a language called Gherkin.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Step definitions connect Gherkin steps to programming code via an expression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary-&quot;&gt;Summary 📝&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the question remains. Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why might we want to write cucumber tests? Bearing in mind that this could be &lt;strong&gt;in addition to unit testing&lt;/strong&gt;. What might we want to achieve? What is the goal of testing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;to-increase-confidence-for-stakeholders-through-evidence---dan-north&quot;&gt;“To increase confidence for stakeholders through evidence - Dan North”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a quote from Dan North - the creator of behaviour driven development. What he means by “stakeholders” is people whose “lives” you touch i.e. your users. But it also can mean product owners, compliance, security, testers, support, other developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cucumber tests are a form of testing, but you wouldn’t just use Cucumber for that, you’re using it to help communicate requirements. To not only increase confidence for stakeholders but also for yourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;external-resources&quot;&gt;External Resources&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cucumber.io/&quot;&gt;https://cucumber.io/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/cucumber/cucumber-js&quot;&gt;https://github.com/cucumber/cucumber-js&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cucumber_(software)&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cucumber_(software)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>James Lieu</name></author><summary type="html">What are cucumber tests and why might they be useful</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pomodoro Technique</title><link href="http://jameslieu.github.io/pomodoro-technique/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pomodoro Technique" /><published>2020-08-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-08-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://jameslieu.github.io/pomodoro-technique</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://jameslieu.github.io/pomodoro-technique/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been using the Pomodoro technique for work. It greatly improves time management and boosts productivity. I’ve been reflecting on why it’s been so effective for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/pomodoro-technique-1.png&quot; style=&quot;height:150px;margin:0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-the-pomodoro-technique&quot;&gt;What is the Pomodoro technique?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;. the Pomodoro Technique is a time management method developed by Francesco Cirillo.
The technique uses a timer to break down work into intervals, traditionally 25 minutes in length, separated by short breaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are six steps in the original technique:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decide on the task to be done.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set the pomodoro timer (traditionally to 25 minutes).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work on the task.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;End work when the timer rings and put a checkmark on a piece of paper.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you have fewer than four checkmarks, take a short break (3–5 minutes) and then return to step 2; otherwise continue to step 6.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After four pomodoros, take a longer break (15–30 minutes), reset your checkmark count to zero, then go to step 1.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-experience-&quot;&gt;My Experience 🧔&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been finding myself pretty tired lately, it’s sometimes hard to focus and be productive, so I’ve started applying this technique into my work days to see if this will help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use an application called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.focustodo.cn/&quot;&gt;Focus To-do&lt;/a&gt; and also recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https://tide.fm/en_US/&quot;&gt;Tide&lt;/a&gt; for Android/iPhone&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/pomodoro-technique-2.png&quot; style=&quot;height:200px; float:left&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/pomodoro-technique-3.png&quot; style=&quot;height:200px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.focustodo.cn/&quot;&gt;https://www.focustodo.cn/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having used the Pomodoro technique, I’ve come to realise some of the other hidden benefits it provides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prompts-you-to-work-&quot;&gt;Prompts you to work ⏱&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are days where your motivation to do anything is lower than usual, maybe you didn’t sleep well the night before, maybe you’re feeling mentally drained. Triggering a Pomodoro timer, will prompt you to start work,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;helps-with-focus-&quot;&gt;Helps with focus 💡&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing that I have one pomodoro (25 minutes) to complete a task or two, the mentality of knowing there is a countdown ongoing, encourages me to remain focused on the task at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also helps, to check how much time is left every now and then to consider quickly how I’m progressing and whether I can completely finish the task before the timer runs out or to leave it in a position to pick up where I left off after the break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;helps-with-distractions-&quot;&gt;Helps with distractions 💢&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not uncommon to be distracted while working, whether it’s looking at your phone or browsing the internet. In my experience, I’ve done this a number of times, but when in the middle of a pomodoro session, I’m conscious about the timer ticking away and so I mentally try not to waste it be focusing on the task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;encourages-more-breaks-&quot;&gt;Encourages more breaks ⏳&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having rest breaks will boost energy levels as you work throughout the day. The more you take, the more energy you replenish. But we often don’t realise how long we’ve been working until something distracts us such as going for a loo break, feeling hungry or thirsty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The breaks should be away from your desk or monitor. You’re encouraged to move around or look at something that is not your work monitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, when I’ve worked without many breaks, I tend to be very mentally drained towards the last couple of hours of work and even in the evenings. By adopting the pomodoro technique, the breaks are short and plenty, and for me personally, I’ve found myself to have a lot more energy throughout the day because I had taken the breaks as directed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-considerations-&quot;&gt;Other Considerations 🤔&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This technique doesn’t seem to work for everyone. We’ve tried it during pair programming and the team member whom I was paired with said that It breaks the flow of conversation or the train of thought as 25 minutes intervals are too short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also true for larger meetings of 3 or more people, 25 minutes seems to not be enough time for everyone to contribute to the discussion. If anything, the breaks feels more like an interruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although, we can increase the Pomodoro time to more than 25 minutes. &lt;a href=&quot;https://zoom.us/&quot;&gt;Zoom&lt;/a&gt; has a 40 minute limit for its free plan. I think 40 minutes is a good number for a break between meetings. As meetings itself can be extremely draining if its duration is too long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary-&quot;&gt;Summary 📝&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally like this technique, I think it works very well with programming, especially when you’re sitting in front of the monitor for large portions of the day. I feel less tired in the evenings and at the more productive overall. I don’t use this technique every day but I feel like I should.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our minds needs regular breaks. Trying focus without giving yourself time to recover will likely drain you towards the end of the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would recommend this technique for anyone who is struggling to stay motivated or easily distracted. It is especially helpful when working from home.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>James Lieu</name></author><summary type="html">I've been using the Pomodoro technique for work. It greatly improves time management and boosts productivity. I've been reflecting on why it's been so effective for me.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">100 Days of Pluralsight</title><link href="http://jameslieu.github.io/100-days-of-pluralsight/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="100 Days of Pluralsight" /><published>2020-07-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-07-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://jameslieu.github.io/100-days-of-pluralsight</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://jameslieu.github.io/100-days-of-pluralsight/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve managed to achieve the 100 day learning streak for Pluralsight&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/100-days-of-pluralsight-1.png&quot; style=&quot;height:450px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few months ago, I’ve written a post about &lt;a href=&quot;/how-i-build-habits&quot;&gt;how I build habits&lt;/a&gt;, where I outline a method I use to create habits that allow me to perform tasks consistently in a maintainable way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By applying this method, I have managed to watch Pluralsight daily for &lt;strong&gt;100 days straight&lt;/strong&gt;. I’d thought it would be good to share this milestone as well as reinforce the idea that &lt;strong&gt;small consistent actions can make a big impact on the end result&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By only aiming to watch a minimum of 10 minutes of Pluralsight videos a day, I was able to consume so much content. Here are the receipts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/100-days-of-pluralsight-2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;My Personal Profile as of 24th July 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here is my 100 day learning streak insight. It also states I’ve watched 75+ hours of content, this is not actually the case, Pluralsight does not account for when you watch the courses are a higher speed i.e. 1.5x - 2.0x speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The audio for the videos seem to also be artificially slowed which seems a little disingenuous as it means the courses duration are not quite the length they say they are. I mention this in my &lt;a href=&quot;/pluralsight-review&quot;&gt;Pluralsight review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now onto the courses:
 &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/100-days-of-pluralsight-3.gif&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;All the courses I’ve watched so far as of 24th July 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘red badge’ icon on the left of each course listed, are the ones I’ve completed. There were a few I didn’t finish watching because I either found not relevant, or I was already well-versed on the remaining videos or I’m currently watching them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bear in mind that this history includes courses completed even before the start of my streak. In fact, with the exception of two days (one in March and another in April), I’ve been watching Pluralsight daily since &lt;strong&gt;February 24th 2020&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/100-days-of-pluralsight-4.gif&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;em&gt;My daily streaks up until October (when I purchased the subscription)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember those days I missed, each one I had basically forgotten to watch it that day, they were also days where my evening was unusually busy (on both days). Had I not broken my streak both times, my daily learning streak would’ve been &lt;strong&gt;151 days&lt;/strong&gt; today&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary-&quot;&gt;Summary 📝&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned, I was really only able to achieve this due to &lt;a href=&quot;/how-i-build-habits&quot;&gt;building a habit&lt;/a&gt;. I highly recommend having a read to help you achieve your goals, whether its to exercise more or read more, this is an excellent way to get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will I continue with this habit? Probably, my company did pay for a annual subscription, so it’d be a good idea to get as much value from it as I can. I don’t regret consuming this much content, they’re very educational and very relevant to my career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t look like anything special happens once I reached this milestone. It would be nice for Pluralsight to acknowledge it by sending an email or introduce achievement badges of some sort, perhaps that would encourage me to aim even higher, 200 daily streaks? 1 year? Regardless, its not really that important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would I recommend Pluralsight? &lt;a href=&quot;/pluralsight-review&quot;&gt;See my review here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I’m pretty proud of my 100 day streak milestone!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>James Lieu</name></author><summary type="html">I've managed to achieve the 100 day learning streak for Pluralsight</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Top Tips For Recruiters From a Developer</title><link href="http://jameslieu.github.io/top-tips-for-recruiters-from-a-developer/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Top Tips For Recruiters From a Developer" /><published>2020-06-22T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-06-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://jameslieu.github.io/top-tips-for-recruiters-from-a-developer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://jameslieu.github.io/top-tips-for-recruiters-from-a-developer/">&lt;p&gt;So I recently had create a post on &lt;a href=&quot;/my-experience-with-recruiters/&quot;&gt;My Experience With Recruiters&lt;/a&gt;. I think giving constructive criticism is valuable but providing solutions is probably more useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to give some general feedback this time, to give &lt;strong&gt;my opinion&lt;/strong&gt; on what &lt;strong&gt;I feel would engage me if I were on the market for opportunities&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-know-your-audience&quot;&gt;😀 Know your audience&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My profile specifically states what technology I specialise in i.e. C#, JavaScript, etc.  Why would you then send me a job spec for Java or C++ roles? Sending me applications for technologies I have no experience in, only makes me think that you didn’t even bother reading my profile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Although I respect that you’re trying to get leads, so reading each profile before sending out mass emails makes the process slower, no excuse if you’re calling me on the phone however).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, I’m less likely to work with you if I see that you’re not showing interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I respond the best when the email was tailored to me personally, or when on the phone, the recruiter demonstrates that they’ve read my profile. Even if I’m not on the market for opportunities, I think this kind of customer service is the best, more professional and shows confidence that you know what you’re doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m aware that recruiters are talking to many potential customers and so spending too much time doing this for each of them may not be as ideal. My point is that I’m more likely to be engaged if you did this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-be-creative&quot;&gt;✨ Be creative&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve received so many recruitment emails during my time as a developer. They’re generic enough for me to ignore them completely, meaning I don’t even open them anymore. The ones I do open, have interesting creative subject titles and the content is also interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bear in mind it is possible that many of recipients of these recruitment emails are likely already employed and are not actively looking for roles. If you’re planning to create leads from this audience, it would increase your chances if your email isn’t plain and generic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-communication&quot;&gt;😀 Communication&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most recruiters start off very polite and enthusiastic, but once you’ve submitted your CV with them to forward to their clients, communication quality goes way down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I’m in the process of working with you, some updates to the application would be appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was job hunting, I found that I was the one who had to chase up on the progress on the application, there was on recruiter who actually knew the progress of the applications, but just didn’t bother informing me of it, was a little rude about it as well. That guy I’ll never work with again and I know he recruits with roles that matches my profile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast to this, one of the recruiters who had successfully gotten me a role had such great communication and interpersonal skills that when I were made redundant at said role years later, I had called him first who then had gotten me another role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-stay-in-touch&quot;&gt;🤝 Stay in touch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve managed to get somebody a role. Ask them to give you a recommendation on LinkedIn, every few months or so, send a message to ask how they’re doing, maintaining communications with the ones you’ve worked with in the past can also one day lead to another opportunity to work with said person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I for one often appreciate someone getting in touch just for the sake of saying hi. If you’re trying to sell me something, I may have my guard up however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-know-the-company-youre-recruiting-for&quot;&gt;🏢 Know the company you’re recruiting for&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When selling me a role, I found that I was more impressed with a recruiter when they talk about the company, if they’ve  successfully recruited for them before, met the people there, have an idea of the office environment, knowing what else the company has to offer i.e. Good coffee, bean bag chairs, free fruit etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I have questions that may not be in the job spec, if the recruiter can answer them, it suggests that they have a great relationship with the company as well, which then suggests that working with this recruiter is worth my while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-understand-the-tech-youre-recruiting-for&quot;&gt;💻 Understand the tech you’re recruiting for&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not saying you should learn TDD, but you should at least be aware of what it is or what it means. This includes some of the other items in your spec such as TDD, BDD, Redux, webpack etc&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t need to be an expert on any of these, but being able to explain what the job involves without just reading from the spec can be very engaging for the person you’re trying to recruit. It’s like selling a product to someone, if you don’t really know what you’re selling, it makes it difficult to believe anything you’re saying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary-&quot;&gt;Summary 📝&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is only my opinion and should be taken with a grain of salt. I appreciate that I know nothing of the recruitment industry so my assumptions here can be completely wrong. I’m just providing &lt;strong&gt;feedback from a customer’s perspective&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that recruiters have a bad reputation among the programming industry and perhaps this is due to the lack of feedback from customers such as myself. I’ve had many good and bad experiences, I feel it’s valuable to recognise and celebrate the good while providing constructive criticism for the bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not expert but recruitment feels like a ‘people’ industry more than anything, and so to successfully to sell your ‘roles’ to us, communication is key, build a network and maintain it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, if you’re a recruiter reading this, I hope there are some insights you can take-away from this and I wish you the best of luck.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>James Lieu</name></author><summary type="html">I wanted to give some general feedback this time, to give my opinion on what I feel would engage me if I were on the market for opportunities.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Video Conferencing Etiquette</title><link href="http://jameslieu.github.io/video-conferencing-etiquette/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Video Conferencing Etiquette" /><published>2020-06-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-06-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://jameslieu.github.io/video-conferencing-etiquette</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://jameslieu.github.io/video-conferencing-etiquette/">&lt;p&gt;When I started a new role on June 2019, one of the perks was to be able to work from home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the development team worked from home and only required to come into the office once a week on any day they choose. So our everyday meetings were conducted via video conferencing tools such as ‘Zoom’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remote work is becoming more common in this industry, and attending meetings via video conferencing tools are a necessity for working remotely when working within a team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I thought I’d share a few video conferencing etiquettes I’ve learned and adopted in the past year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-close-all-unnecessary-applications&quot;&gt;💻 Close All Unnecessary Applications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One challenge with online video meetings is to stay focused. It could just be me, but not being in the same room as the speaker or other attendees which seems to reduce my attention span.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found that when I had browser windows opened on my second monitor, I start getting distracted and often try multitasking by browsing while listening to the meeting. It’s a bad habit to have and so closing all browser windows will mitigate this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-mute-yourself-when-not-talking&quot;&gt;🔇 Mute Yourself When Not Talking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although you may not be talking, if you’re mic isn’t muted, then other noise may be picked up and can be distracting to other people in the meeting, especially the person who is speaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also if somebody physically comes to speak to you and you need to respond respond, this interaction will not distract other attendees at the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-raise-your-hands-if-you-wish-to-speak&quot;&gt;✋ Raise Your Hands If You Wish To Speak&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When in meetings, it would gracious to raise your hand or provide some indication that you have a question or can add to the discussion. You may end up speaking over other people otherwise. Although this only works if your webcam is on and the attendees can see you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-sit-away-from-your-keyboardmouse&quot;&gt;⌨ Sit Away From Your Keyboard/Mouse&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional tip to avoid being distracted. Keeping your keyboard and mouse away will hopefully you focus your attention on the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-keep-your-mobile-phone-away&quot;&gt;📵 Keep Your Mobile Phone Away&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your phone can be a big distraction, if you receive a notification or end up browsing on your phone, it is not only rude but takes your attention away from the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-request-breaks&quot;&gt;☕ Request Breaks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should hope that the meeting host be responsible for managing the time within the meeting as well. But sometimes, that’s not the case and if the meeting is going far too long without a break, it is not unreasonable to request 5-10 minutes to fetch a glass of water, a hot beverage or use the bathroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-checking-out-of-the-meeting&quot;&gt;👋 ‘Checking-out’ Of The Meeting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one is uncommon but I think is important, when you’re in a meeting and you feel you’re getting no value from it, I feel like you should be able to request to leave the meeting when the opportunity presents itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember in my team, we had a QA engineer who is a regular attendee at our development meetings, but often we end up in a technical discussion which is of no value to the QA engineer I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So during our retrospective, I had made the suggestion or request that we can ‘check-out’ of the meeting if we find that the meeting doesn’t require our attendance. While I didn’t specifically say, but I requested this primarily for my colleague (the QA engineer) although, I think it’s valuable to have the option to check-out for myself as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-turn-on-webcam&quot;&gt;🟢 Turn on Webcam&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When in a video call and having a conversation with someone or a group, being able to see them is generally more pleasant than not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re communicating with your webcam on, people can see your facial expressions, reactions, acknowledgments and even see whether you’re present in the call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: sitting in a well-lit room will help with the picture quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-turn-off-webcam-if-you-need-divert-your-attention&quot;&gt;🔴 Turn off Webcam if you need divert your attention.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you need to leave your desk or physically talk to someone, turning off your webcam will reduce any distraction to the other attendees, having this a common practice among your team will communicate to them that you’re occupied with something else temporarily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary-&quot;&gt;Summary 📝&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not being in the same room as other people changes how you interact and pay attention during the meeting. For example, not paying attention because you’re typing at your keyboard or looking at your phone is equally rude whether you’re physically at the meeting or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something I realized by not only being guilty for some of these bad habits, but also witnessing some colleagues doing it either when I’m the speaker or just another attendee. So these are a few tips I recommend when attending online meetings.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>James Lieu</name></author><summary type="html">Remote work is becoming more common in this industry, and attending meetings via video conferencing tools are a necessity when working within a team. So I thought I'd share a few video conferencing etiquettes I've learned and adopted in the past year.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Self-reviewing Your Code</title><link href="http://jameslieu.github.io/self-reviewing-your-code/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Self-reviewing Your Code" /><published>2020-06-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-06-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://jameslieu.github.io/self-reviewing-your-code</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://jameslieu.github.io/self-reviewing-your-code/">&lt;p&gt;Self-reviewing your code is, in my opinion, just as important as having someone else review it before it gets approved and deployed. It is akin to proof-reading an email you wrote before sending it; checking that you haven’t missed anything, whether there are errors or whether there are areas you can refine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not self-reviewing adequately is probably more common than we think, I myself have been guilty of doing this. When you think you’re done coding your feature, it is easy to skim through your changes (diff) or not look at them at all. Submit the change. Then let your colleague review it while you work on a new and more exciting task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-should-we-self-review-our-work-&quot;&gt;Why Should We Self-Review Our Work? 🤔&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is conceptually the same reason we proof-read any emails or any writing intended for someone else. You’ll want to catch errors, look for areas which can be refined and check if anything was missed or had been forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often re-reading your code again can give you further confidence that what you’ve worked on is done to a standard that you deem acceptable when contributing to the product you’re working on. Also, depending on the size of the work, when working on a particular feature long enough can reduce the likelihood that we’ll to remember &lt;strong&gt;exactly&lt;/strong&gt; what was added and what was removed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-the-worse-that-could-happen-&quot;&gt;What’s the worse that could happen? 🤷&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the perspective as a developer for a company, it depends on the scenario really, if you’re working on a system that is only used within the company internally then it’s not as detrimental if you deploy work that breaks the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example is a product that doesn’t have any ‘live’ users. There is more leeway for errors or issues under these circumstances. Although, it will not only cause inconvenience for you but for your team members as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is, however, very serious if the system is used by clients or customers and is a source of revenue for your company. In under any circumstances should anyone be deploying work without being absolutely certain that the changes do not break the system unknowingly. It’s bad for the customer, its bad for the team and it’s bad for the company. Everybody is unhappy, so being extra careful when making changes or updates to the system is paramount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reviewed-by-somebody-else-&quot;&gt;Reviewed by somebody else 🕵&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a standard practice to have your code reviewed by someone else before it gets released to production. We’re all human and are not infallible, having a second pair of eyes on your code to check for errors, look for improvements and to make sure that it meets the requirements is very valuable and should not be taken for granted when working in a team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code review process has some acceptable trade-offs. The first is that it requires a member of your team to ‘review’ said code, which means that time needs to be allocated to that task. The reviewer will need to read the code and if there is feedback or changes requested, then the code owner needs to either go back to modify the code or to have a discussion about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This takes up a fair amount of time and even more so, if there were obvious defects in the code which would’ve been spotted had the developer been more vigilant with reviewing their own work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having the reviewer leave feedback for ‘commented-out’ code or typos are not only embarrassing but requires time allocated to fix it. Vigilantly self-reviewing your code can at least mitigate those kinds of errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s arguably selfish to leave the fault-finding to the reviewer, as mentioned previously, this review process can take time. How can we expect someone else reviewing your work and to be vigilant if we don’t abide by the same standard. At the very least, the developer ought to respect their own work by self-reviewing and making sure that what they’re submitting is done to a high standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relying on the reviewer to find those because they feel that reviewing their own code will ‘slow’ them down is not only egotistical but a disservice to themselves as the more mistakes they submit, the less confidence the rest of the team will be in the quality and skills of said developer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-my-personal-experience&quot;&gt;🧔 My Personal Experience&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I once had a colleague who did exactly this. He likes to work quickly which &lt;a href=&quot;/writing-code-too-quickly&quot;&gt;has it’s own problems&lt;/a&gt;, he would open a pull request and then move onto the next task. When I began the code review, it was very often littered with issues, commented out code, code that was used for debugging purposes i.e. &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;console.log(&quot;here!!!!&quot;)&lt;/code&gt; etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the review, it needs to go back into progress, but my colleague would often be in the middle of the next task, which meant that he wouldn’t pick up the work that was reviewed until the next day or even a few days after depending on how long it would take him to complete the task he was currently working on (which then a PR is created for it for review).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because there was little self-review even for working on the feedback on the first PR, when that one goes back into review, it is not uncommon for that one to also have issues or require changes again. So the cycle continues&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem was that reviewing like this takes a lot of time. Although the code owner felt he was being very productive, but in terms of the productivity from the team as a whole, we were at risk of not completing all the work we had allocated for that sprint. Productivity is compromise and all he had to do is read his own code to reduce the odds of the work to require updates or changes, especially for the obvious defects such as commented out code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bear in mind that I also have tasks of my own that I need to complete (and have reviewed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary-&quot;&gt;Summary 📝&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To summarize the key points why self-review is important and worth the time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check we haven’t missed anything&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check whether there are errors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check for areas for refinement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can identify areas of improvement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A better team code review experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think habit of self-reviewing your code is one of the things that will improve the quality of the code you write. We’re not infallible and should almost expect to write code that is imperfect. Self-reviewing simply allows us to allocate time to &lt;strong&gt;think&lt;/strong&gt; about what was written, check for issues or anything you’ve forgotten or to look for ways to improve it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>James Lieu</name></author><summary type="html">Self-reviewing your code is, in my opinion, just as important as having someone else review it before it gets approved and deployed.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Should You build a Programming Portfolio?</title><link href="http://jameslieu.github.io/should-you-build-a-programming-portfolio/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Should You build a Programming Portfolio?" /><published>2020-06-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-06-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://jameslieu.github.io/should-you-build-a-programming-portfolio</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://jameslieu.github.io/should-you-build-a-programming-portfolio/">&lt;p&gt;As an aspiring developer, it is good to have a portfolio of projects to not only build knowledge and experience with the technology you’re using but to use as code examples for when applying for a job as a programmer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I wonder whether potential employers actually look at these projects? (Genuine question)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I were in the shoes of an employer or responsible for hiring a developer, will I really look at &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; of the projects in a programmers portfolio?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe I’ll randomly select a few however, but even then I probably will skim through the logic or check for things like unit tests. I probably wouldn’t pull it down onto my local machine to run or even check that the tests even pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I myself have a portfolio of projects in my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jameslieu?tab=repositories&quot;&gt;github profile&lt;/a&gt;, I doubt employers look at each individual projects in any detail at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My point is, is there really that much value creating a large number of projects for your portfolio? They can take a lot of time depending on what your project is and having too many will decrease the chances of a potential employer to look at them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-personal-experience-&quot;&gt;My Personal Experience 🧔&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned earlier, I have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jameslieu&quot;&gt;Github profile&lt;/a&gt; where I place all of my personal projects.  When attending job interviews, the only time somebody had mentioned it was when they saw a repository called &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jameslieu/project_euler&quot;&gt;project_euler&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as of 18th June 2020, I only have a single completed code challenge in there. Had I had more code challenges in there I think the interviewer/developer would’ve been more impressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do have a repo called &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jameslieu/csharp_projects&quot;&gt;csharp_projects&lt;/a&gt; which has a variety of code challenges as well as personal projects (specifically written in C#) all within the same repo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(The reason I had organized it this way was because I wanted to branch off from PHP to C# professionally which was difficult to do without taking a pay cut, so this repo was the one I sent to potential employers to boost my chances.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In hindsight, I think having the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jameslieu/csharp_projects&quot;&gt;csharp_projects&lt;/a&gt; repo helped, but the amount of time it had taken to build all of these was very costly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I had a single solid project with all of the bells and whistles, deployed for the interviewer to demo, I think that would’ve had a greater impact than all of those smaller projects. Also, having a repo for code challenges would’ve gotten more attention more so than the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary-&quot;&gt;Summary 📝&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having built many projects and having a sizable portfolio, from a job hunting perspective, I think it actually deters interviewers from actually looking at them at all. I think it would be better to have only 1-2 great (sizable) projects and a repo dedicated to solving programming problems i.e. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jameslieu/project_euler&quot;&gt;project_euler&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The projects you build should be built with the technology you’re applying with. For example, if I were to apply for ASP.Net Core roles, then ideally that project should be built with ASP.Net Core.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having fewer projects will increase likelihood that the potential employer will actually look at your projects. Then having the coding problem repo will be the one where you can demonstrate how you solve programming challenges.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>James Lieu</name></author><summary type="html">As an aspiring developer, it is good to have a portfolio of projects to not only build knowledge and experience with the technology you're using but to use as code examples for when applying for a job as a programmer.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Are Meetings Necessary?</title><link href="http://jameslieu.github.io/are-meetings-necessary/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are Meetings Necessary?" /><published>2020-06-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-06-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://jameslieu.github.io/are-meetings-necessary</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://jameslieu.github.io/are-meetings-necessary/">&lt;p&gt;Meetings are a great way to communicate with people within your company. However, they can be huge productivity killers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is a particular meeting even necessary? If you’re meeting for an hour, one perspective is that its not only one hour that is lost, but one hour multiplied by the total number of attendees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think meetings should only be called after a consensus is reached that the meeting is &lt;strong&gt;necessary&lt;/strong&gt;. What does it mean for a meeting to be necessary? The two factors I can think of is &lt;strong&gt;coordination&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;conflict&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-coordination&quot;&gt;🤝 Coordination&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For when a decision requires collaboration from different people. This includes people within a team, other teams or departments. The decision could be in regards to a feature that needs to be built and so,  speaking only to the relevant people to have a decision made on what their requirements and expectations are is why this meeting is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-conflict&quot;&gt;🤼 Conflict&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For when there are disagreements from two or more parties. A meeting in this instance can also be necessary to resolve this conflict and that a consensus has been reached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-pros-and-cons&quot;&gt;The Pros and Cons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meetings are important and useful, but can also be counter-productive by taking time away from actually getting work done. In my opinion, some of the pros and cons are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pros-&quot;&gt;Pros 👍&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;-you-may-be-part-of-the-decision-making&quot;&gt;✌ You may be part of the decision making&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This kind of activity can help you feel like a valuable member of the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;-you-may-be-able-to-contribute-and-share-knowledge-to-other-attendees&quot;&gt;💡 You may be able to contribute and share knowledge to other attendees&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There may be times where your experience or knowledge can have an impact and so sharing that can only be positive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;-receive-relevant-information&quot;&gt;📰 Receive relevant information&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is important if its related to work you’re involved in. You may only be listening during the meeting but the content may be insightful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;-you-can-ask-questions&quot;&gt;📢 You can ask questions&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don’t understand something or require further clarity, being present during the discussion allows you to ask questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cons-&quot;&gt;Cons 👎&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;-the-meeting-may-not-be-relevant-to-you-in-particular&quot;&gt;🤷 The meeting may not be relevant to you in particular&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned before, attending meetings will cost your time and attention. If the contents of the meeting isn’t relevant to you, then you could be spending your time and attention on other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;-you-may-have-nothing-to-add-to-the-discussion&quot;&gt;😫 You may have nothing to add to the discussion&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is related to the above point, the meeting isn’t relevant to you and you have nothing to add, then why is your attendance even necessary? Better to use that time on more pressing tasks&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;-it-can-be-mentally-draining&quot;&gt;😩 It can be mentally draining&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is often overlooked. People in your team, likely has different energy thresholds for long meetings. I often feel extreme fatigue when a meeting has ended. Finding the energy and motivation to start a new task or continue where I left off can be challenging and therefore severely reduces productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;-reduces-your-productivity&quot;&gt;☹ Reduces Your Productivity&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re in the middle of a task, having to pause and attend a meeting which may not even be relevant to you is sure to affect your overall productivity. Although you can work around this by with good time management provided the meeting was scheduled with enough time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;do-you-need-to-attend-&quot;&gt;Do You Need To Attend? 🤷&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some meetings &lt;strong&gt;are&lt;/strong&gt; necessary. But we should ask ourselves, “do &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; need to attend”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When meetings are scheduled, it may be relevant to you personally and so your attendance will provide you value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue is, that we often find ourselves attending meetings, while relevant to other people, is not relevant for you. Meaning, had you not attended that particular meeting, you could’ve been doing something else, something more productive and useful with that time instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;-some-practices-to-consider&quot;&gt;🧍 Some Practices To Consider&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being more aware about the meetings you have and conscious how much time they take, it’s worth considering adopting some practices:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-dont-meet-unless-absolutely-necessary&quot;&gt;🏃 Don’t meet unless absolutely necessary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find out why you’re meeting; is a meeting necessary? Consider that if you’re meeting for an hour, it’s not just an hour of company time that is being lost; it’s the hour multiplied by the total number of people in attendance. Meetings should only be called after a consensus has been reached that a meeting is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-set-a-time-limit&quot;&gt;⏱ Set A Time Limit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting a time limit to a suitable length, most people will lose their ability to pay attention the longer the meeting continues. Having a meeting for 15-30 minutes for example can at least guarantee that the attendees are not experiencing too much fatigue. Another benefit of this, is that the people speaking will be encouraged to ‘get to the point’ and be more concise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-ask-people-to-prepare-in-advance&quot;&gt;✍ Ask People To Prepare in Advance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel meetings should not be used for brainstorming. Having a clear agenda, topics, questions or reading sent to all attendees in advance can make the meeting overall more productive. Thinking ahead and preparing for the meeting will help if you’re not good at ‘thinking on your feet’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary-&quot;&gt;Summary 📝&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meetings have their pros and cons. They’re important but I think it’s also a good idea to be mindful about how much time they cost.
How much productivity is lost as a result of attending meetings?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think attending meetings where you’re an active participant is important and has value, but for those where you’re not, would it not, be just as effective if you were cc’d an email from an attendee with a written summary, key-points or the decisions from said meeting? Food for thought.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>James Lieu</name></author><summary type="html">Meetings are a great way to communicate with people within your company. However, they can be huge productivity killers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Writing Code Too Quickly</title><link href="http://jameslieu.github.io/writing-code-too-quickly/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Writing Code Too Quickly" /><published>2020-06-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-06-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://jameslieu.github.io/writing-code-too-quickly</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://jameslieu.github.io/writing-code-too-quickly/">&lt;p&gt;Writing Code very quickly does not necessarily mean you’re being more productive and can actually increase the amount of time to complete a task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When writing an email, it’s not uncommon to not realise that there are errors or something missing (i.e. file attachments) in the email before you send it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These problems are also present when coding. Not taking the time to plan and proof-read you code can lead to problems which are easily mitigated if you adopt a slower and more methodical approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-process-&quot;&gt;The Process 📝&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to “try” to write code very fast. I would write code quickly but often not identifying the problem and solving it in a sensible way. I would find that I’m spending an large amount of time debugging but at the same time not really understanding the problem I’m trying to solve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, when a unit test is failing, I discover where I think the problem is, start to tweak it, and run the test to see if it passes, if it fails I repeat that process again and again until it passed. It looked something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 1:&lt;/strong&gt; Make a change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 2:&lt;/strong&gt; Run test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 3:&lt;/strong&gt; If the test fails, repeat step 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine doing this over and over until the test finally passes. During this process, because I’m ‘rushing’, there can be typos or missing characters in my changes, which I only discover because the tests notified me when it failed or if the complier fails the build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that didn’t work, I would do a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;/copy-and-paste-programming&quot;&gt;copy-and-pasting&lt;/a&gt; either with blocks of logic or functions from the source code with slight changes. Or I look on the internet for solutions and copy the code from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a decent typing speed and using a few keyboard shortcuts on the IDE motivated me to churn out code as quickly as I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sounds like a great at first glance but there were some serious flaws with this way of working. So I thought I might list my opinions on the pros and cons of this style of coding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pros-&quot;&gt;Pros 👍&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-you-feel-more-productive&quot;&gt;💪 You feel more productive&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll find that you’re very focused on the task, typing in so many lines of code, running your unit tests to get them to pass as you debug or tweak the logic to correct a bug or issue with the application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you’re doing this, time is going by very quickly, you feel good at how focused and productive the day has been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-its-sometimes-faster&quot;&gt;🏃 It’s sometimes faster&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The increased speed in which you’re working can mean that you’re getting things done faster, providing that the solution you’ve written works and there were no issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If enough time and effort is spent on the requirements and prerequisites prior to coding, then often this way of working is fine and feels great when you have a plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cons-&quot;&gt;Cons 👎&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll list the ones based on my own experience as well as some ideas how to address them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-youre-more-prone-to-mistakes&quot;&gt;🤦 You’re more prone to mistakes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re more likely to make these mistakes if you don’t pace yourself; things like typos, using the wrong variable or misreading the code can really halt your productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solution: Pace yourself, focus on one step at a time and be sure to read your code as you write it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-you-dont-read-the-code&quot;&gt;🙄 You don’t read the code&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll find that ‘skimming through’ the code is faster and matches your pace of working. This is more obvious when self-reviewing your own code, rushing to push the code up as soon as possible can encourage you to ‘skim through’ your code and risk missing any flaws with the code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the issues you might introduce are typos, refactoring opportunities, commented-out code, unused code and duplication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solution: Read your code often.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-you-havent-actually-identified-the-problem-youre-trying-to-solve&quot;&gt;😬 You haven’t actually identified the problem you’re trying to solve&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The urge to start coding before coming up with a plan can hide what the real solution or problem is. The solution often isn’t something that’s obvious, you may have an idea how to write it, but what if that idea is incorrect?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has happened to me numerous times. You’ll spend hours on a task only to realise that your solution is flawed or even wrong.
You can be so focused on the task that you don’t realise the time and have spent potentially hours on it before asking for help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You speak to a co-worker to see if they can help you, and you both immediately realise that your solution needs to be updated or improved. Even worse if you end up realising this as you were explaining problem to begin with. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rubber_duck_debugging&quot;&gt;Rubber duck debugging&lt;/a&gt; 🦆&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solution: Take a moment to make sure you understand the problem, it helps to plan how you’re going to tackle the problem by writing a checklist or some key points on what the problem is.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-you-forget-something&quot;&gt;🙊 You Forget Something&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only are you more likely to make mistakes when coding too quickly, you’re more likely to miss something. When you’ve finally gotten that unit test to pass. You may feel that you’re done, commit your code and push your changes without thinking whether you may need to do anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common example would be to run the full test suite again, new logic you have written may have broken another part of the system. So the tests will fail and you’ll need to fix it. It is especially bad if the test suite takes a very long time to run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another key example is the organization of your work, particularly for version control. A good practice when working with Git for example is to commit regularly and to keep your commits. When working too quickly, you may forget to commit and if  you’re working on a large feature. This can be problematic if you haven’t completed the work and you needed to commit the code to hand-over to someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solution: Commit and self-review your own code regularly&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-you-spend-more-time-debugging&quot;&gt;🐞 You spend more time debugging&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably the main sign and negative aspect of coding too fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your code doesn’t work and you find yourself chasing tons of bugs and issues.
You end up spending more time trying to fix problems rather than think about the problem and solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solution: Code a little bit at a time, test and verify it before moving on to the next step.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-you-lose-understanding-of-how-your-code-works&quot;&gt;🙉 You lose understanding of how your code works&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When working this way, after a while of trying to fix the bug, you may find that you’ve made so many changes and tweaks to get the tests to pass, that you’ve changed too much and no longer know what you’re code is doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so you’ll attempt to undo (&lt;strong&gt;CTRL+Z&lt;/strong&gt;) everything in order to get it back to the state it was in before all of those changes you made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solution: Take a step back and make sure you understand the problem and the solution.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary-&quot;&gt;Summary 📝&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often those who write the code the fastest in terms of time are those who are methodical and slow about the process. Attempting to rush the work can lead to many problems if you’re not careful. Slowing down and being methodical in your way of working is not only a safer but also less stressful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers aren’t measured on how fast they write code but by the quality of the solution and how well it works and maintainable it is. The best code is written slowly and purposefully, not quickly with the intent of meeting an arbitrary deadline.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>James Lieu</name></author><summary type="html">Writing Code very quickly does not necessarily mean you're being more productive and can actually increase the amount of time to complete a task.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Programmer Notes: Software Construction</title><link href="http://jameslieu.github.io/programmer-notes-software-construction/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Programmer Notes: Software Construction" /><published>2020-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://jameslieu.github.io/programmer-notes-software-construction</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://jameslieu.github.io/programmer-notes-software-construction/">&lt;p&gt;This is part of my &lt;strong&gt;“Programmer Notes”&lt;/strong&gt; series where I leave notes in the form of a blog post here based on something I’ve read or learned. See &lt;a href=&quot;/improve-retention-rate-when-learning/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; for more context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-construction&quot;&gt;What is Construction?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know what “construction” means when it’s used outside software development. “Construction” is the work “construction workers” do when they build a house, a school, or a skyscraper. When you were younger, you built things out of “construction paper”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In common usage, “construction” refers to the process of building, the process might include some aspects of planning, designing, and checking your work, but mostly “construction” refers to the hands-on part of creating something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-software-construction&quot;&gt;What is Software Construction?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developing software is a complicated process. Researchers have identified numerous distinct activities that go into software development. They include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Problem definition&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Requirements development&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Construction planning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software architecture, or high-level design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Detailed design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coding and debugging&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unit testing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integration testing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;System testing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Corrective maintenance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Construction is mostly coding and debugging but also involves detailed design, construction planning, unit testing integration testing, and other activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Construction is also sometimes known as “coding” or “programming” “Coding” isn’t really the best word because it implied the mechanical translation of a preexisting design into a computer language; construction is not at all mechanical and involves substantial creativity and judgment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some specific tasks involved in construction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Verifying that the groundwork has been laid so that construction can proceed successfully&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Determining how your code will be tested&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Designing and writing classes and routines&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating and naming variables and named constants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Selecting control structures and organizing blocks og statements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unit testing, integration testing and debugging your own code&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reviewing other team members’ low level designs and code and having them review yours&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Polishing code by carefully formatting and commenting it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integrating software components that were created separately&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tuning code to make it faster and use fewer resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-is-software-construction-important&quot;&gt;Why Is Software Construction Important?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you agree that improving software development is important in general, the question is Why is construction an important focus?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;construction-is-a-large-part-of-software-development&quot;&gt;Construction is a large part of software development&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on the size of the project, construction typically takes 30 to 80 percent of the total time spent on a project. Anything that takes up that much project time is bound to affect the success of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;construction-is-the-central-activity-in-software-development&quot;&gt;Construction is the central activity in software development&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Requirements and architecture are done before construction so that you can do construction effectively. System testing (in the strict sense of independent testing) is done after construction to verify that construction has been done correctly. Construction is at the center of the software-development process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;with-a-focus-on-construction-the-individual-programmers-productivity-can-improve-enormously&quot;&gt;With a focus on construction, the individual programmer’s productivity can improve enormously&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A study (1968) showed that the productivity of individual programmers varied by a factor of 10 to 20 during construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;constructions-product-the-source-code-is-often-the-only-accurate-description-of-the-software&quot;&gt;Construction’s product, the source code, is often the only accurate description of the software&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many projects, the only documentation available to programmers is the code itself. Requirements specifications and design documents can go out of date, but the source code is always up to date. Consequently, It’s imperative that the source code be of the highest quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;construction-is-the-only-activity-thats-guaranteed-to-be-done&quot;&gt;Construction is the only activity that’s guaranteed to be done&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ideal software project goes through careful requirements development and architectural design before construction begins. Imperfect real-world projects, however, often skip requirements and design to jump into construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They drop testing because they have too many errors to fix and they’ve run out of time. But no matter how rushed or poorly planned a project is, you can’t drop construction. Improving construction is thus a way of improving any software development effort, no matter how abbreviated&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-points&quot;&gt;Key Points&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software Construction is the central activity in software development; construction is the only activity that’s guaranteed to happen on every project.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The main activities in construction are detailed design, coding, debugging, integration, and developer testing (unit testing and integration testing)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Other common terms for construction are ‘coding’ or ‘programming’&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The quality of the construction substantially affects the quality of the software.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your understanding of how to do construction determines how good a programmer you are.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McConnell, S., 2004. &lt;em&gt;Code Complete, Second Edition.&lt;/em&gt; Redmond (Washington): Microsoft Press.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>James Lieu</name></author><summary type="html">What is software construction? And why it is important?</summary></entry></feed>